<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>expressive | DRAFT Head Start Arts</title>
    <link>/tag/expressive/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/expressive/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>expressive</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>expressive</title>
      <link>/tag/expressive/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview</title>
      <link>/post/interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/interview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTERVIEW can be a great way to give students a chance to verbalize things that are going on in their imaginations.  It is most successful when used soon after the students have had an experience where they used both body and voice to pretend that they are a character in a story.  Because of this it is a perfect follow up to SOLO but it might be interesting to use following an active time in the dramatic play area of a classroom.  Depending on the student&amp;rsquo;s prior knowledge, it might be helpful to show them photos/video of news interviewers in action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Video of interview routine]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-1&#34;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell students they will pretend to be a character from a story as you pretend to be an interviewer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[image of a recording device]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-2&#34;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show the students the imaginary microphone you will use a prop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna demonstrating the imaginary microphone]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is amazing what a powerful difference it makes when students speak into an imaginary microphone.  It can be anything&amp;hellip; a simple drum stick or even a wooden spoon.  As long as the teacher commits to pretending it is picking up their voice, students follow right along and instinctively &amp;ldquo;take&amp;rdquo; to the idea of speaking directly into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-3&#34;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Model an example of an interview question with improvised answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna and a helper modeling an interview question being asked three times and answerd in three different improvised ways]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the students are very young and new to INTERVIEW it is really worth the time to model improvised answers to interview questions. Be sure to model a range of answers from complex to a simple single word response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-4&#34;&gt;Step 4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefly demonstrate for the students the audio recording device you use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna having the puppets help them with  recording a &amp;ldquo;testing one two three&amp;rdquo;  and then listening to it together]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young students are very excited to hear their own voices on an audio recording; sometime it&amp;rsquo;s even more captivating than seeing themselves on video, which has become a more common part of daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-5&#34;&gt;Step 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Begin the interview!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna putting on a costume piece etc.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It really helps to find a way to transition yourself and the students from &amp;ldquo;normal time&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;pretending time&amp;rdquo; and back again when the interview is over.   It could be as simple as putting on a hat or turning around or changing your tone of voice and/or even turning on the audio recording device.  Keep in mind that your own level of engagement in the pretending sets a bar of expectation for the students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-6&#34;&gt;Step 6&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask  one or more open ended questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna interviewing puppets as though they are the gingerbread man]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As students answer your interview questions, remember to expand on answers that are brief into complete sentences.  Keep your questions open-ended; for example: &amp;ldquo;What happened?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;How did you or feel when&amp;hellip;?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;What is fun about being a gingerbread man?&amp;rdquo; To maximize engagement and minimize wait time, divide the class into small groups and delegate the role of interviewer to several adults in the room so that several interviews can be happening simultaneously then regroup to share out all together as a group. &lt;br&gt;
Some preschoolers are even ready to take on the role of interviewer themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-7&#34;&gt;Step 7&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a break!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this highly focussed verbal activity, the students often need some kind of kinesthetic break such as a dance break or recess before listening to their audio recording.  You might even want to hold of on having them sit still to listen to their audio recording until the end of the day or the next morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-8&#34;&gt;Step 8&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen to the interview!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[image of students listening to recording-I think I have one]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students are captivated at listening for the sound of their own voices and words on the recording.  As you listen together, silently celebrate each voice that you hear by pointing out who is speaking with a gesture or even a colored flashlight.  After the interview is over, describe  a few choices that you noticed students making with their improvisations: times when you could hear them loud and clear, times when they added interesting words, times when they sounded like their character etc.  Consider having student ECHO some of these choices together as a whole class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-9-optional&#34;&gt;Step 9 (Optional)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider adding follow up interviews during choice time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the fun of recording interviews has been established, consider making it a part of choice time by interviewing students individually and listening to their recorded voices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
