<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>language | DRAFT Head Start Arts</title>
    <link>/category/language/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/language/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>language</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>language</title>
      <link>/category/language/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Freeze</title>
      <link>/post/freeze/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/freeze/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Freeze is a simple but effective warm up! You create a cue for instant silent stillness. Children practice responding to your cue. This routine ensures students can engage in (sometimes chaotic) dramatic movement safely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-1&#34;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Model the Freeze routine&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-2&#34;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invite a single volunteer to try responding to the Freeze cue&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young children may not be able to freeze every single body part. That is ok! Draw children&amp;rsquo;s attention to some part of the volunteer&amp;rsquo;s body that is frozen (hand, arm, elbow, shoe).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-3&#34;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invite a new volunteer to respond to the Freeze cue&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, reinforce the intention of the Freeze routine by drawing attention to a part of the volunteer&amp;rsquo;s body that was instantly silent and still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-4&#34;&gt;Step 4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now invite the whole class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure to name and affirm a success for each child before continuing on with the rest of the warm up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add variations such as body parts (wiggle your arms, legs, head, shoulders etc.) or levels (wiggle up high, down low etc) or speed (wiggle fast and slow).  This is a wonderful opportunity to introduce and reinforce rich new vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview</title>
      <link>/post/interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/interview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;INTERVIEW can be a great way to give students a chance to verbalize things that are going on in their imaginations.  It is most successful when used soon after the students have had an experience where they used both body and voice to pretend that they are a character in a story.  Because of this it is a perfect follow up to SOLO but it might be interesting to use following an active time in the dramatic play area of a classroom.  Depending on the student&amp;rsquo;s prior knowledge, it might be helpful to show them photos/video of news interviewers in action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Video of interview routine]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-1&#34;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell students they will pretend to be a character from a story as you pretend to be an interviewer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[image of a recording device]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-2&#34;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show the students the imaginary microphone you will use a prop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna demonstrating the imaginary microphone]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is amazing what a powerful difference it makes when students speak into an imaginary microphone.  It can be anything&amp;hellip; a simple drum stick or even a wooden spoon.  As long as the teacher commits to pretending it is picking up their voice, students follow right along and instinctively &amp;ldquo;take&amp;rdquo; to the idea of speaking directly into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-3&#34;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Model an example of an interview question with improvised answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna and a helper modeling an interview question being asked three times and answerd in three different improvised ways]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the students are very young and new to INTERVIEW it is really worth the time to model improvised answers to interview questions. Be sure to model a range of answers from complex to a simple single word response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-4&#34;&gt;Step 4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefly demonstrate for the students the audio recording device you use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna having the puppets help them with  recording a &amp;ldquo;testing one two three&amp;rdquo;  and then listening to it together]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young students are very excited to hear their own voices on an audio recording; sometime it&amp;rsquo;s even more captivating than seeing themselves on video, which has become a more common part of daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-5&#34;&gt;Step 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Begin the interview!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna putting on a costume piece etc.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It really helps to find a way to transition yourself and the students from &amp;ldquo;normal time&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;pretending time&amp;rdquo; and back again when the interview is over.   It could be as simple as putting on a hat or turning around or changing your tone of voice and/or even turning on the audio recording device.  Keep in mind that your own level of engagement in the pretending sets a bar of expectation for the students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-6&#34;&gt;Step 6&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask  one or more open ended questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna interviewing puppets as though they are the gingerbread man]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As students answer your interview questions, remember to expand on answers that are brief into complete sentences.  Keep your questions open-ended; for example: &amp;ldquo;What happened?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;How did you or feel when&amp;hellip;?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;What is fun about being a gingerbread man?&amp;rdquo; To maximize engagement and minimize wait time, divide the class into small groups and delegate the role of interviewer to several adults in the room so that several interviews can be happening simultaneously then regroup to share out all together as a group. &lt;br&gt;
Some preschoolers are even ready to take on the role of interviewer themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-7&#34;&gt;Step 7&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a break!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this highly focussed verbal activity, the students often need some kind of kinesthetic break such as a dance break or recess before listening to their audio recording.  You might even want to hold of on having them sit still to listen to their audio recording until the end of the day or the next morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-8&#34;&gt;Step 8&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen to the interview!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[image of students listening to recording-I think I have one]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students are captivated at listening for the sound of their own voices and words on the recording.  As you listen together, silently celebrate each voice that you hear by pointing out who is speaking with a gesture or even a colored flashlight.  After the interview is over, describe  a few choices that you noticed students making with their improvisations: times when you could hear them loud and clear, times when they added interesting words, times when they sounded like their character etc.  Consider having student ECHO some of these choices together as a whole class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-9-optional&#34;&gt;Step 9 (Optional)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider adding follow up interviews during choice time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the fun of recording interviews has been established, consider making it a part of choice time by interviewing students individually and listening to their recorded voices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solo</title>
      <link>/post/solo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/solo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Solo allows you guide your students through a portion of a story plot while they imagine that they a main character. Use SOLO when your story has a main who enacts a sequence of physical actions, like the Very Hungry Caterpillar who eats lots of food, builds a chrysalis then emerges as a flying butterfly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another good example is Max from Where the Wild Things Are, who stares into the eyes of the Wild Things then dances, swings from trees, and marches with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video here of solo]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-1&#34;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose a story&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[picture of storybooks]
image:
caption: &#39;&#39;
focal_point: &#39;&#39;
preview_only: no&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-2&#34;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a sequence of active prompts following the physical actions of the main character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[picture of a handwritten version of the solo script ]
image:
caption: &amp;lsquo;Example Solo Script&amp;rsquo;
focal_point: &#39;&#39;
preview_only: no&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see in this script example, it helps to begin each line of the narrative with an active verb. In a traditional narrative pantomime students do not make sound, but in some instances it can work nicely to add a brief repetitive line for the character to speak aloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-3&#34;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the book to the children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna reading the story to wolf and bear]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your group should be familiar with the story from previous readings. Before reading, tell the group they will soon pretend to be this character. Encourage everyone to pay special attention to what the character does in the story as you read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-4-optional&#34;&gt;Step 4 (optional)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the need of your students, model the acting out of the solo for the students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of either susanna modeling or susanna having isaak model while susanna reads the solo aloud]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have dual language learners in your classroom is can be very helpful to model the solo for them first.  There are a couple of ways to do this.  You can model it yourself by telling the narrative in first person and acting it out as you talk, for example &amp;ldquo;I am the gingerbread boy.  You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t believe what happened to me the other day.. I was a ball of dough&amp;hellip; &amp;quot; or if you&amp;rsquo;re lucky you might have another adult caregiver in the room willing to pantomime the actions, following your prompts as you read the narrative for them.&amp;rdquo;  Either way, very young students appreciate the chance to see an adult in their life willing to take a risk and being playful and dramatic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-5&#34;&gt;Step 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give everyone enough room to move!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of tape, circle spots etc.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to make sure every student has a specific spot on the floor where they have a bubble of space around them; where they will remain throughout their solo.  Some classrooms call this a &amp;ldquo;kinesphere&amp;rdquo;. Generally, if while standing in their spot they can put their arms out in front, to their sides and behind them without touching another child they will have the space they need.  Sometimes we mark each student&amp;rsquo;s spot on the floor with a piece of tape or a circle spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-6&#34;&gt;Step 6&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice the challenging parts of the solo together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna leading echo with the puppets]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the moments in your solo are going to be more challenging than others for the students to act out.  It&amp;rsquo;s a good idea to try identify what they are ahead of time and give the students a chance to practice them before the solo begins. In this instance the teaching artist identified things like showing you are a lump of dough, running fast without leaving your spot, getting eaten up, and saying the line &amp;ldquo;Catch me if you can!&amp;rdquo;  The ECHO warm up that we taught you in a previous video can be very helpful here.  A few rounds of ECHO can also give you an opportunity to remind the children that the don&amp;rsquo;t have to copy the model that you just demonstrated exactly.  Rather, remind them that you hope they will act out the story in their own unique and different way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-7&#34;&gt;Step 7&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Narrate the solo while they act it out&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna reading the solo while the puppets act it out]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You really want to keep your eye on the students as they pantomime the solo.  Sometimes they need more time and so you might find yourself repeating the same word or line several times&amp;hellip; like &amp;ldquo;You run! and run! and run!&amp;rdquo; Other times you will discover that they&amp;rsquo;re getting tired sooner than you expected so you might find yourself editing a few moments out of your originally planned script.  Be a storyteller! If you bring enthusiasm and engagement to your narration they will be inspired to put that energy into their performances.  We describe SOLOs as &amp;ldquo;parallel play&amp;rdquo; in that the students are all performing simultaneously but not interacting with one another; consequently they&amp;rsquo;re a great low risk way for all students to become performers in the classroom because there is no audience watching them to make them feel self-conscious.  Depending on the story, sometimes they are slow and gentle, other times they can be a terrific cardio experience.  For highly active SOLOs it can be helpful to begin them in a moment of stillness, and then return gradually to stillness at the end so that the students have a time to cool down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-8&#34;&gt;Step 8&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember and re-enact favorite moments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna and puppets reflecting together and susanna expanding on one of the pupp&amp;rsquo;s answers ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the needs and age of the class, it can work well to reflect after the SOLO by ask &amp;ldquo;What is choice you made that you liked from your solo?” If the language in their answer is incomplete, take a moment to expand on their answer before inviting the volunteer to perform their moment for the class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;or-perform-the-solo-for-one-another-again&#34;&gt;Or&amp;hellip; perform the solo for one another again.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[video of susanna and wolf watching bear perform together and susanna asking wolf what she notices ]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other times, particularly with older students it works well to divide the class in half with students on one side of the room being audience and the other side being performers on the stage.  Have the performers perform the solo again for the audience, invite the audience to tell the performers what they likes about their pantomime before switching places so that everyone has had a chance to act out the solo in front of an audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;great-books-for-solo-in-prek&#34;&gt;Great Books for Solo in PreK&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where the Wild Things Are
The Gruffalo
Snow Day [list all with links and authors]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
