<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>background | DRAFT Head Start Arts</title>
    <link>/tag/background/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/background/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>background</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>background</title>
      <link>/tag/background/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arts Integration and Language</title>
      <link>/post/arts-integration-and-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/arts-integration-and-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most people agree that young children need many opportunities for positive interaction with adults to develop healthy emotions and language skills. Children have these experiences with their adults who care for them, including parents and teachers. Teachers in Head Start gain insight in how to provide these experiences though standards in classroom interactions on the CLASS, and see their results when observing children, like with the DRDP or the TS Gold. But how do we plan these interactions, and how do we make them fun, developmentally appropriate, and part of our regular classroom routines?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way is to integrate arts-based instruction into our regular instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We created this series of videos for you! They model basic drama techniques. You can use these videos while you plan your own lessons integrating arts into your work with children. We have included step by step moves, from planning to implementation, for how to integrate verbal and non-verbal scaffolds that specifically support children as they wind their way toward literacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We intend to help you make connections between socio-emotional and literacy outcomes embedded within your work with children, as they are represented in the CLASS.  We hope you will be able to integrate the techniques into your lesson plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all play is equal. We all play to have fun - and a certain kind of play supports early literacy development - Play does not always mean social interaction. Playful interaction does not necessarily support early literacy. When a child&amp;rsquo;s play is interactive and interpersonal, based on fantasy and enacted through verbal or non verbal communication - we call it &amp;ldquo;social pretend play,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;fantasy play,&amp;rdquo; and it supports early literacy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
